<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.0.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2019-12-04T15:22:54-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">wes bonelli</title><author><name>wes bonelli</name></author><entry><title type="html">Spirography</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2019/12/04/spirography.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Spirography" /><published>2019-12-04T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2019-12-04T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2019/12/04/spirography</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2019/12/04/spirography.html">&lt;p&gt;I stumbled across a cool problem presented &lt;a href=&quot;http://codyraskin.com/research/?p=158&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; by Cody Raskin. His post is short, so I’ll reproduce it in full:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Suppose you had a circle made of a hundred or so equidistant points on its circumference. If you drew straight lines connecting distant points on this circle (chords) in some systematic way, you’d produce a kind of spirograph. I don’t know what these plots are actually called, and “spirograph” is actually just the brand-name of a popular toy, but in any case, most people have probably drawn something like this at some point in their lives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The most common form of these that I’ve encountered are ones where the pattern for connecting the points is to simply connect every point &lt;em&gt;p&lt;sub&gt;i&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/em&gt; to &lt;em&gt;p&lt;sub&gt;i + k&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/em&gt; where &lt;em&gt;k&lt;/em&gt; is some fixed offset. What if instead we connected &lt;em&gt;p&lt;sub&gt;i&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/em&gt; to &lt;em&gt;p&lt;sub&gt;ik&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/em&gt; where &lt;em&gt;k&lt;/em&gt; is now a fixed multiplier?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I used the Desmos graphing calculator to play around with different values of &lt;em&gt;k&lt;/em&gt; in real time. I did not expect the “lobe” count to scale as &lt;em&gt;∝ k−1&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I wonder if someone could come up with some hand-wavy argument as to why this behaves this way? In any case, you can try it out at Desmos &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.desmos.com/calculator/yjayzmpgzr&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These things are kind of beautiful. I don’t recall ever drawing one when I was a kid. To make up for it, I’ve tried to reason through the question with the help of &lt;a href=&quot;https://d3js.org/&quot;&gt;D3.js&lt;/a&gt;. (Let me know if I got anything wrong, please!)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you haven’t clicked on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.desmos.com/calculator/yjayzmpgzr&quot;&gt;Desmos link&lt;/a&gt; yet, I encourage you to fiddle with it and see if you can get a sense for how it works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s start at the beginning, which also happens to be the end. Where’s that? The rightmost point on the graph. We can refer to it as &lt;em&gt;p&lt;sub&gt;0&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/em&gt; (that is, &lt;em&gt;p&lt;sub&gt;i&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/em&gt; where &lt;em&gt;i&lt;/em&gt; = 0). We increment &lt;em&gt;i&lt;/em&gt; (the “index” of the current point) as we progress counter-clockwise around the perimeter. The spirograph is &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Modular_arithmetic&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;modular&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, like a clock: &lt;em&gt;i&lt;/em&gt; “wraps around” after some maximum value, back to &lt;em&gt;i&lt;/em&gt; = 0. In the graph Cody has given us that value is &lt;em&gt;i&lt;/em&gt; = 500, so we say we’re using arithmetic modulus 501, or &lt;em&gt;n&lt;/em&gt; = 501. This means 0 and 501 are &lt;em&gt;congruent&lt;/em&gt;, or interchangeable, in this system. So are 1 and 502, 2 and 503, and so on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is called a &lt;em&gt;congruence relation&lt;/em&gt;, and we can say it exists when (&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Modular_arithmetic#Definition_of_congruence_relation&quot;&gt;per Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;a and b have the same remainder when divided by n.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s as if we’ve cut a slice (of length &lt;em&gt;n&lt;/em&gt;) out of the number line, curled it into a loop, and glued the ends together. If you take &lt;em&gt;n&lt;/em&gt; steps from &lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt; and call the place you arrive &lt;em&gt;b&lt;/em&gt;, you’ll discover &lt;em&gt;b&lt;/em&gt; is actually &lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before considering the multiplier case, let’s think about the offset case: each point &lt;em&gt;p&lt;sub&gt;i&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/em&gt; connects to point &lt;em&gt;p&lt;sub&gt;i + k&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/em&gt;. Most of us are probably familiar with at least two of the forms this pattern produces: the pentagram (&lt;em&gt;n&lt;/em&gt; = 5, &lt;em&gt;k&lt;/em&gt; = 2) and the Star of David (&lt;em&gt;n&lt;/em&gt; = 6, &lt;em&gt;k&lt;/em&gt; = 2). Grab a piece of paper and try it out if you don’t believe me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The operative difference between the offset case and the multiplier case is the relationship between &lt;em&gt;i&lt;/em&gt; and the distance between &lt;em&gt;p&lt;sub&gt;i&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/em&gt; and the point it connects to (as measured in counter-clockwise “hops” between adjacent points) on the perimeter of the graph. Let’s call this distance &lt;em&gt;d&lt;/em&gt;. In the offset case we know by definition that &lt;em&gt;d&lt;/em&gt; = &lt;em&gt;k&lt;/em&gt;. If we plotted  &lt;em&gt;d&lt;/em&gt; as a function of &lt;em&gt;i&lt;/em&gt;, we’d get a horizontal line at &lt;em&gt;k&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now consider the multiplier case, wherein &lt;em&gt;p&lt;sub&gt;i&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/em&gt; connects to &lt;em&gt;p&lt;sub&gt;ik&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/em&gt;. Thus &lt;em&gt;d&lt;/em&gt; is no longer constantly &lt;em&gt;k&lt;/em&gt;, but &lt;em&gt;ik&lt;/em&gt;. There’s a catch, though: we’ve got to observe the rules of modular arithmetic. Points on our graph are only numbered from 0 to &lt;em&gt;n&lt;/em&gt; - 1, after all. So what happens if (in standard arithmetic) &lt;em&gt;ik&lt;/em&gt; &amp;gt; &lt;em&gt;n&lt;/em&gt;? We substitute for it the &lt;em&gt;congruent&lt;/em&gt; integer &lt;em&gt;c&lt;/em&gt; such that 0 ≤ &lt;em&gt;c&lt;/em&gt; ≤ &lt;em&gt;n&lt;/em&gt;. How do we find it? Easy: just take &lt;em&gt;ik&lt;/em&gt; mod &lt;em&gt;n&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wait a second. What happens when we take &lt;em&gt;p&lt;sub&gt;i&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/em&gt; and try to connect it to point &lt;em&gt;p&lt;sub&gt;ik&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/em&gt;, but find that &lt;em&gt;ik&lt;/em&gt; = &lt;em&gt;c&lt;/em&gt; = &lt;em&gt;i&lt;/em&gt;? We can try to draw a line from a point to the very same point, but if we’re sufficiently precise, we won’t get very far! These strange, self-referential spots deserve a deeper look.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When does &lt;em&gt;ik&lt;/em&gt; = &lt;em&gt;i&lt;/em&gt;? When &lt;em&gt;i&lt;/em&gt; = 0, to begin with. Hence the very first step in constructing any spirograph according to this sort of pattern: just connect the initial point to itself. When else? When &lt;em&gt;ik&lt;/em&gt; = &lt;em&gt;n&lt;/em&gt;, since &lt;em&gt;p&lt;sub&gt;n&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;p&lt;sub&gt;0&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/em&gt; (this is equivalent to the example above, where we started from &lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt;, took &lt;em&gt;n&lt;/em&gt; steps, and ended up back at &lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Points which connect to themselves (save for the initial point) indicate that a &lt;em&gt;cycle&lt;/em&gt; has been completed: that is, &lt;em&gt;p&lt;sub&gt;ik&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/em&gt; has “caught up to” &lt;em&gt;p&lt;sub&gt;i&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/em&gt;. One will always find &lt;em&gt;k&lt;/em&gt; - 1 cycles because &lt;em&gt;p&lt;sub&gt;ik&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/em&gt; ultimately “travels” &lt;em&gt;k&lt;/em&gt; times farther than &lt;em&gt;p&lt;sub&gt;i&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/em&gt;, and must “lap” it &lt;em&gt;k&lt;/em&gt; - 1 times. If we were to plot &lt;em&gt;d&lt;/em&gt; for the multiplier case, we would get a sine wave with domain [0, &lt;em&gt;n&lt;/em&gt; - 1] and range [0, &lt;em&gt;n&lt;/em&gt; / 2]. Intuitively, lobe count scales at &lt;em&gt;k&lt;/em&gt; - 1 because each darkly-shaded cycle is a kind of “shadow” directly opposite to a lightly shaded “lobe”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Shading” is lighter within each lobe and darker without because as you move away from a lobe center and nearer to a midpoint between lobes, each point’s outgoing connection line departs further from the tangent and approaches orthogonality: that is, the line bisects the circle. At bisection, &lt;em&gt;p&lt;sub&gt;i&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/em&gt; is maximally distant from &lt;em&gt;p&lt;sub&gt;ik&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/em&gt;. Outgoing connections swing back toward the tangent as you move toward the center of the next lobe. Dark shading occurs in small “nodes” near bisection initial points (opposite “lobes”) and forms lobe boundaries where chords “stack” tightly around the tangent line. Here’s what that looks like for  &lt;em&gt;k&lt;/em&gt; = 2 and &lt;em&gt;k&lt;/em&gt; = 4:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;codepen&quot; data-height=&quot;265&quot; data-theme-id=&quot;light&quot; data-default-tab=&quot;js,result&quot; data-user=&quot;w-bonelli&quot; data-slug-hash=&quot;NWPPgrm&quot; style=&quot;height: 265px; box-sizing: border-box; display: flex; align-items: center; justify-content: center; border: 2px solid; margin: 1em 0; padding: 1em;&quot; data-pen-title=&quot;Spiro_k2&quot;&gt;
  &lt;span&gt;See the Pen &lt;a href=&quot;https://codepen.io/w-bonelli/pen/NWPPgrm&quot;&gt;
  Spiro_k2&lt;/a&gt; by w-bonelli (&lt;a href=&quot;https://codepen.io/w-bonelli&quot;&gt;@w-bonelli&lt;/a&gt;)
  on &lt;a href=&quot;https://codepen.io&quot;&gt;CodePen&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://static.codepen.io/assets/embed/ei.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;codepen&quot; data-height=&quot;265&quot; data-theme-id=&quot;light&quot; data-default-tab=&quot;js,result&quot; data-user=&quot;w-bonelli&quot; data-slug-hash=&quot;eYmmRZp&quot; style=&quot;height: 265px; box-sizing: border-box; display: flex; align-items: center; justify-content: center; border: 2px solid; margin: 1em 0; padding: 1em;&quot; data-pen-title=&quot;Spiro_k4&quot;&gt;
  &lt;span&gt;See the Pen &lt;a href=&quot;https://codepen.io/w-bonelli/pen/eYmmRZp&quot;&gt;
  Spiro_k4&lt;/a&gt; by w-bonelli (&lt;a href=&quot;https://codepen.io/w-bonelli&quot;&gt;@w-bonelli&lt;/a&gt;)
  on &lt;a href=&quot;https://codepen.io&quot;&gt;CodePen&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://static.codepen.io/assets/embed/ei.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;TL;DR:&lt;/strong&gt; “Lobes” correspond to cycles in the spirograph. Each cycle is preceded by a bisection. Each bisection entails a small, darkly-shaded “node” near its initial point, and a larger, lightly-shaded “lobe” directly opposite.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now my lobes are tired. That’s it for this post. Thanks again to Cody for providing the basis for it.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>wes bonelli</name></author><summary type="html">I stumbled across a cool problem presented here by Cody Raskin. His post is short, so I’ll reproduce it in full:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Words</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2019/11/25/words.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Words" /><published>2019-11-25T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2019-11-25T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2019/11/25/words</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2019/11/25/words.html">&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“…the leaf is the cause of the leaves.” - Friedrich Nietzsche&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Are words real?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps they are, you respond. Take fiction. One can hold it in one’s hand. Look: here’s a &lt;em&gt;Chronicles of Narnia&lt;/em&gt;. C.S. Lewis was real, and so are his words, and so are his books. I own a few of them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what of the ideas? The characters? The worlds? Are they real?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ah, now, surely not, you say. One shan’t meet Aslan nor find Narnia no matter how many wardrobes one wanders into. Then again, one might find him on an article of childrens’ clothing, or a lunchbox. But no matter. Fiction is born in the imagination, and what happens in the imagination isn’t real.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well now, I say, I’m stymied. Here before us lies a thing with which we decorate our children and their accessories. It’s all in one’s head? It isn’t real?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don’t be ridiculous, you sputter. Clearly it is real, in a way. Lewis thought about it, then wrote about it, then millions read him and thought about it some more. A film and plenty of merchandise were made. Aslan the &lt;em&gt;idea&lt;/em&gt; is real. Aslan the &lt;em&gt;lion&lt;/em&gt; is not. On this we agree, yes?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, sure. But consider what we’ve just said: Aslan the &lt;em&gt;idea&lt;/em&gt; is real, and Aslan the &lt;em&gt;lion&lt;/em&gt; is not. What is Aslan the lion?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One might be forgiven for losing patience with this extended dramatization. I’m being deliberately dense, one might judge. This is not unreasonable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll say it again: are words real?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The causalist, Hacking tells us&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, might say yes. Like electrons, we can spray them at things with consistent results. For instance, I can spew “Don’t pay attention to your tongue” into the void and thus ensure you’ll do the opposite. Other things, like Yeti or &lt;em&gt;later&lt;/em&gt; (as in, “I’ll do it later”), aren’t real, because we can’t seem to locate or deploy them predictably. Where we can point to a cause, per this view, we can say a thing is real.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It took Faraday a lifetime to convince himself of the reality of the electromagnetic force&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Isn’t it proper that we entertain similar skepticism? Says Nietzsche:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“What is a word? The image of a nerve stimulus in sounds.”&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Does a word simply stand in for otherwise unmanageable complexity? Do words ever cause things to happen? Did you become aware of your tongue because I told you not to? Because some arcane symbols I arranged caused your neurons to fire in a peculiar way? Because the force-field ripples we call particles obeyed the rules physicists have so meticulously derived for them? What does it mean to think causality at diverse scales?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In certain situations, Hofstadter points out,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“the bottom level, though 100 percent responsible for what is happening, is nonetheless irrelevant to what happens.”&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He goes on to ask how one might best explain a prime-finding algorithm. Is it best to outline the computational medium’s mode of operation? Or to describe the nature of prime numbers and the essence of the strategy for their detection? For that matter, could one not object that the algorithm might not today be known were Euclid never to have discovered (or invented) primes? Any single reply, given independently, adopts a restricted view of a limited space. Meanwhile cause shimmers nearly everywhere one looks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Faraday did convince himself, in the end.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2:2&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/zNVQfWC_evg?t=804&quot;&gt;Tong puts it well&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“…this was Farraday’s genius: to appreciate that, even though you can’t see anything in between [two magnets] — even though, no matter how closely you look, the space between the magnets will seem to be empty — there’s something real there.”&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:4&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:4&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We too might fruitfully consider the inevitability that there are regions of reality which we cannot directly or do not typically sense. This is not a new idea: much modern science rests on &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Construct_(philosophy)&quot;&gt;constructs&lt;/a&gt; measured exclusively by proxy. Of hierarchical systems, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cs.utexas.edu/~EWD/transcriptions/EWD03xx/EWD361.html&quot;&gt;Dijkstra posits&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“…the number of levels that can be distinguished meaningfully… is kind of proportional to the logarithm of the ratio between the largest and the smallest grain.”&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:5&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:5&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whether there exists a bijection between “that which is” and “that which is hierarchical” I can’t say. But this idea gracefully captures the necessarily limited nature of human cognition, I think. How ought we determine whether the grains we think we observe — from quarks, to fields of force, to ideas, to words, to wills, to identities, to ideologies, to values, to social facts, to cities, to cultures, to corporations and nations, to black holes, to dark matter, and so on — correspond sufficiently closely to &lt;em&gt;real&lt;/em&gt; things they purport to denote? Do we not increasingly negotiate (and shape) consensus reality with language? How to avoid fallacies of reification? How to understand the various interwoven techniques of vocalization, inscription, transmission, and computation which have swollen with such vigor from the first words spoken some hundred thousand years ago?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/All_models_are_wrong&quot;&gt;Box’s aphorism&lt;/a&gt; helps, here. He and Luceno assert that&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“…any model is at best a useful fiction… Nevertheless enormous progress has been made by entertaining such fictions and using them as approximations.”&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:6&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:6&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Says Morton:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“The first task is to abolish the idea of the possibility of a metalanguage that could account for things while remaining uncontaminated by them… [but] some metaphors are better than others.”&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:7&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:7&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Words refract. They glow faintly. Some, like “red”, twinkle in ways no one can precisely characterize except that they’re &lt;em&gt;just so&lt;/em&gt; — unless one feels that “the subjective quality of the visual experience of electromagnetic radiation with wavelength between 625 and 740 nanometers” is all there is to say about it. In any case none emit light themselves. Things and beings do. Words bend it and slice it. Negative spaces emerge: distinctions. It’s hard to see the lines, though. It’s dark in here. The light flickers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Marx, at least in his youth, held:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“…the object itself must be studied in its development… [until it is] put alongside something else… [it] remains a mere abstract conception in space and does not develop into anything further.”&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:8&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:8&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maturana channels him:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“…the observer can describe an entity only if there is at least one other entity from which he can observe it to interact or relate. This second… can be any entity, but the ultimate reference for any description is the observer himself.”&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:9&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:9&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Conway%27s_law&quot;&gt;Conway&lt;/a&gt;, he maintains:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“…the logic of the description and, hence, of behavior in general, is necessarily the logic of the describing system.”&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:9:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:9&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Derrida called his work an&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“‘operation’, if you will… which, although it is consumed by the reading of other texts, in a certain fashion refers only to its own writing.”&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:10&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:10&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;10&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How ought one define the thing which itself must make up the definition? Nietzsche warned:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“The ‘thing in itself’ is quite incomprehensible to the creators of language and not at all worth aiming for.” &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1:2&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Heidegger tried anyway (here I conceal the object of his discussion, since it is the form which is of interest):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“We are now no longer interpreting [X] in terms of [Y], nor comparing it with [Z]… Although we dealt directly with [X] itself - indeed precisely because of this - we have shirked in the face of [X]. We have indeed not spoken of other things… but of [X] yet not directly and concretely from &lt;em&gt;out of it&lt;/em&gt;, but &lt;em&gt;about it&lt;/em&gt;.”&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:11&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:11&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;11&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Words are like black holes. They open to view and close to scrutiny. What do we see when we look at them? Accretion disks, sometimes: bits of stuff, or sensations, or memories, slowly circling. Warped images from around and behind. They feed on — into — others of their kind. Deictic words are up-front about it. Discourse-deictic words are a little self-conscious.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Words are sharp, I think: they have a point. Where is it? They point fingers. They have something like gravity. Usually they sling you around between them. Occasionally they suck you in and spit you out. You’re moving — really moving — and then you’re out of orbit and right &lt;em&gt;here, now&lt;/em&gt;. The page might swim a little. Sometimes the ears ring. You wonder if maybe somebody close to you died, like Yoda: there’s been a disturbance in the Force. You look back at what you read. It did something to you, when you zipped through it the first time. You’re pretty sure it didn’t damage you; nothing hurts. But something inside you moved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Formal systems, like natural languages, are shifty. Godel interrogated them and found their self-descriptions incomplete. Tarski proved them incapable of defining their motives. Said Poincare:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Mathematics is the art of giving the same name to different things.”&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:12&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:12&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;12&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nietzsche, similarly:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“…every concept originates through our equating what is unequal.”&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1:3&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where &lt;a href=&quot;http://abel.math.harvard.edu/~mazur/preprints/when_is_one.pdf&quot;&gt;Mazur writes&lt;/a&gt; “mathematical objects”, I have (I think justifiably) substituted “words”:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“To define the [words] we intend to study, we often — perhaps always — first make it understood, more implicitly than explicitly, how we intend these [words] to be presented to us, thereby delineating a kind of super-[word]; that is, a species of [word] garnished with a repertoire of modes of presentation. Only once this is done do we try to erase the scaffolding of the presentation, to say when two of these super-[words] — possibly presented to us in wildly different ways — are to be considered equal. In this oblique way, the [words] that we truly want enter the scene only defined as equivalence classes of explicitly presented [words]. That is, as specifically presented [words] with the specific presentation ignored, in the spirit of ‘ham and eggs, but hold the ham.’”&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:13&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:13&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;13&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I take this to mean we’re always touching the elephant somewhere. But it’s uneven and slippery and we can’t really see it. Parts of it are prickly. Sometimes one feels tempted to stop struggling. It’s a bit like ironing a stubborn shirt: you can only get the kinks out of one or two regions of the fabric at once. The wrinkles don’t disappear. They just show up elsewhere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that I think of it, I’ve got some laundry to fold.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Nietzsche, Friedrich. &lt;em&gt;On Truth and Lie in an Extra-Moral Sense.&lt;/em&gt; 1873. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;sup&gt;4&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Hacking, Ian. &lt;em&gt;Representing and Intervening: Introductory Topics in the Philosophy of Natural Science.&lt;/em&gt; 2010. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:3&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Hofstadter, Douglas. &lt;em&gt;I Am a Strange Loop.&lt;/em&gt; 2008. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:4&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;“Quantum Fields: The Real Building Blocks of the Universe.” Performance by David Tong, &lt;em&gt;YouTube&lt;/em&gt;, The Royal Institution, 15 Feb. 2017, www.youtube.com/watch?v=zNVQfWC_evg. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:4&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:5&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Dijkstra, Edsger W. &lt;em&gt;Programming as a Discipline of Mathematical Nature.&lt;/em&gt; 1974. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:5&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:6&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Box, George, and Lucěno Alberto. &lt;em&gt;Statistical Control by Monitoring and Feedback Adjustment.&lt;/em&gt; 1997. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:6&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:7&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Morton, Timothy. &lt;em&gt;Hyperobjects: Philosophy and Ecology after the End of the World.&lt;/em&gt; 2014. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:7&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:8&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Marx, Karl. &lt;em&gt;Difference Between the Democritean and Epicurean Philosophy of Nature.&lt;/em&gt; 1841. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:8&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:9&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Maturana, Humberto. &lt;em&gt;Biology of Cognition.&lt;/em&gt; 1970. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:9&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:9:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:10&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Derrida, Jacques. &lt;em&gt;Positions.&lt;/em&gt; 1981. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:10&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:11&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Heidegger, Martin. &lt;em&gt;The Fundamental Concepts of Metaphysics: World, Finitude, Solitude.&lt;/em&gt; 1983. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:11&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:12&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Eves, Howard. &lt;em&gt;Foundations and Fundamental Concepts of Mathematics.&lt;/em&gt; 1958. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:12&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:13&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Mazur, Barry. &lt;em&gt;When is thing equal to some other thing?&lt;/em&gt; 12 June 2007. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:13&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>wes bonelli</name></author><summary type="html">“…the leaf is the cause of the leaves.” - Friedrich Nietzsche1 Nietzsche, Friedrich. On Truth and Lie in an Extra-Moral Sense. 1873. &amp;#8617;</summary></entry></feed>